okay let
start uh the first of the nine levels is
called s uh s means
mind means to apply the mind to start
the mind off uh so s j
means your first childlike attempt to
put your mind on a particular object
okay that's that's the first
level it's character by NE Nea means uh
the Mind does reach the object okay uh
the mind you do you do choose an object
today for example we're going to choose
as an object our teacher whoever is your
heart teacher it could be Gandhi it
could be someone who's not alive anymore
it could be someone you haven't met yet
and you just emphasized about or if
you're fortunate then you already have a
heart teacher and you will be meditating
on heart teacher
and particularly their eyes so s j how
do you know that you reached level
number one is if in the next 10 minutes
that teacher comes to your mind once
okay usually it's at the
beginning it's the first 20 seconds I
found and uh you bring up your teacher
and then you think about the emails you
didn't get to before you came and then
10 minutes later the teacher says okay
let's stop there and then sometimes
you're lucky that your teacher pops up
you see your teacher again for 20
seconds and then you that's it so s
means the mind is is on the object but
just briefly at the beginning maybe and
and then maybe a few times in between
and then some at the end so we can say
that the NAA or the staying on the
object is only
momentary and my my teacher k used to
like to compare it to a fly on a piece
of poop he is pretty graphic okay it's
a he he would say uh there were okay
I'll tell you the whole story there were
two FES in in Pasa City and they landed
on a
cowpie and uh so they're having a
discussion since it was near the Bala
and they were in the side of where
the they were having a philosophical
and about Nana and her and then they got
to a point um about discussion and one
fly said to another do do you think
there's clears in paradise and the other
one said I don't think so then he said
said well why do you think you want to
go there
anyway Mor being that we live po okay
and we like
it uh so why are they bring that up oh
because
flies they just land per second and then
they decide they want to go to another
part of the poop and then they they keep
going like that so you can think of
level one as the fly on the poop level
all right where your mind is just
jumping around and it comes back Reas
the the Nappa the thing is infinitely
shorter than the young one which means
the time B you to so uh that's the same
joke but the the goal by the
way and and what I want you to think
about the whole 10 days the the real
sort of goal that I'd like you to think
about the whole 10 days is it's
interesting
meditation I think can be more concisely
or or clearly
described as keeping your mind on one
thing just one thing so I I would even
change the word inet in or in Sanskrit
in which means one thing you know just
keep your mind on one thing so the
struggle what i' like it to think of the
word
meditation as aabra maybe we should call
it Agra it will be can you just have one
thing that you're thinking about and
nothing else the meditation can you just
have your teacher image there and
there's nothing else there's nothing
else in the world which which
technically means that you would
die sitting there if you were good at it
because you would forget to come out you
see you would forget to drink or eat or
you know anything you would just sit
there if your concentration is really
good you probably have to have someone
to Jessa went into someone somebody had
to come back to the temple it's like a
he was in a meeting like this and then
everybody went and had lunch you know
and then in the evening they came back
and he was still there and they they had
to wake him up cuz he forgot to go to
lunch you know he because he was just
thinking about one things so I guess
technically if you're good at it you
wouldn't remember to stop medicating or
even the alarm if the alarm went off you
you hear right and it gets to that point
okay so you have to have a you know when
you go swimming in the ocean supp to
have a a buddy maybe if you were a
really good medit you have to have to
wake you to shake you up you know to
knock you out of meditation so it should
be like that I want you to start
thinking of
meditation as as your
mind tied to a single thing I I
visualize it as the way they picture
those Adams they what do you call
those those toys that
have connecting things
between when we were toys TI toys
yeah so there were little dislikes
things with h on the side and then you
you had
a you're going have trouble translating
this into Chinese
latu you had a little stick between and
that
happens that's okay anyway there's a
your mind is one of the Tinker toy discs
and then the AE which is going to be a
teacher's face her eyes is going to be
another teach door piece and then you're
going to be linking them and there's no
other uh links to anything there's
another object it's just that one so
just think that there's no other
connection to any other object there's a
single L and there's a single object and
there's one Tinker toy stick between
them and there's no side sticks going
off to emails or what you left you know
the things you get done before you came
or or lunch or how cold it is or even
just try to picture your mind as a
single unit the object is a single unit
and they are tied together to that's in
okay so that's that's
meditation
is is that
virtuous see like car like no and he's
right okay it's it's karmically neutral
all right it's an instrument like is a
is a
microscope uh
virtuous you see it's just a tool it's
just an instrument I I read we went to a
city in China where there had been some
atrocities during World War II and and
they used microscopes to on living
humans that they cut open to observe
living blood you know and then they blew
them up with grenades to see to to uh
to develop new treatments for soldiers
right so that would be a a non virtuous
use of a microscope that would be an
evil use of a microscope and then um you
know microscopes are used to save lives
every day so meditation is similar it's
comically neutral it's just a tool it's
just an instrument so then that's very
important to understand okay it's it's
just an instrument you can turn
meditation upon anger thinking about
your last exboyfriend or girlfriend or
whatever and and you can concentrate and
they can be you can be obsessed on them
and think about how bad they are you
know and that's a non virtuous use of
the microscope because it's just a an
instrument right and try to keep it un
Mony so I'm going to just talk for 5 10
minutes at a time and then we'll do a
10minute meditation and then we we'll
flip talkop like that it's called
ropa so get
fromation and like Christy when she does
a b class she always gives people this
guilt trip that uh the person next to
you is on the verge of see
young and you
snipple and then they spend 24,000 more
lives suffering okay so I wouldn't say
that to
[Music]
you there's nothing wrong with not
okay once it starts just let it go you
your mou when that
happens all right our only goal for the
first session is to go we're going to go
through the preliminaries the
traditional
preliminar in a different part of the
Tex which you'll be studying Main in a
year uh he he goes through the BL days
very care but right now we just them
together and then we'll stop then we'll
talk some more about
watch the breath in your coming in and
out of your nose place your mind like a
senty at the tip of the nost
just watch the gra
pass
e e
mind are a single object breath mind TI
to a single
object e
ask teacher to come to this
place
second sing in front of you knees to
KN you can feel the war of your body you
can feel their breath in your face you
can smell the pr of
SC
thank you teacher
[Music]
offing SK
s
landscape and then sprinkle it
with some good D youve done in the last
hours e
take something the
last
close you
got coming to treat
[Music]
B e
equal time and effort equal time and
effort thinking about something
to e
think of something you saw someone else
do
[Music]
something are people prep
L of our
own spend Mons
[Music]
let's make a picture in your mind who
you'd like to
be by the end of this 10 days what would
you like to
change you happen simply by wishing who
would you like to be at the end of these
10 days what change should be brought in
in
you in a picture of yourself as you
would like yourself today in
ask your teacher your heart teacher
whoever it
is ask them to help you become in these
10 days we our blessing in the next 10
days to make the changes practice the to
see
and ask your teacher to stay with
you we can't go anywhere we can't suce
anything without teacher our teacher
ask them even if they are hisorical
[Music]
someone around you now ask them in their
spirit it's someone you hope to meet in
the future ask them to come be with you
stay with you for the rest of your life
open the second level medit is
called you means continuity or
stream say variation called
you which me can mean Tantra for example
meaning the scheme of the secret teach
um or the stream mream into that is
called also so so g means any kind of
[Music]
stream Chinese
is uh but it's a a stream of anything so
G again means the application of the
mind to object so g j means your mind is
on your
object uh and instead of being the fly
on the cine uh there's some continuity
it stays on the object for more than a
second so you do have some flow on the
object
so the second level is where you're able
to keep your mind on the object for
short periods of time importantly in the
first and second levels the period of
time on the object is much briefer than
comp time okay so you know if you're
keeping
score you want to know where you
are at level two uh and level one uh the
the time on the object is is defined as
briefer than the okay so if you kep
score of seconds or minutes on the
object uh the time off the object would
be more
in the time on the object in the first
two levels I would say most of this are
level two I believe I I sometimes so uh
more time off the op than not but there
is some continuity like you have 5
Seconds five uninterrupted seconds on on
your teacher's face before you think of
the the noise of the heater or or
someone Banks a cup we have to negotiate
with these guys
uh later maybe Afters I think we have to
betic and we have to mostly let people
know what your times are that you know
and not to just run in there
and okay uh and that's the same with
your family okay you can take this as a
you can take this as
a a metaphor for your life you know
you're going to have to negotiate with
the people around you about like the
people smashing the cups in here uh
you're going to have to negotiate with
the people in your life and it's what's
the easiest way is to people can handle
that you're not going to be around and
know if it's predictable so you have to
make your meditation times predictable
to your family members or your friends
and they have to understand and it has
to be negotiated kindly and fairly you
know you have responsibility
them uh and you have to go in and you
know reasonably you have to
say and then if it's predictable it's
more likely to be uh successful in
negotiation so from you know we're going
to be meditating from 9:30 to
10:30 and but from 10:30 you can smash
all the cups you want because we going
to beog you like that so then you kind
of give and take that's just a metaphor
for your meditation practice for the
rest of your life make
it things can be negotiated with your
family and friends if it's predict and
if it's clear ahead of time
not okay
um so the first two
Ls s
say so fly on the cire and then uh
some to
some is a m who
knows a negative statement that implies
positive
statement someity means not much okay
all
right
now the goal of this week as far as your
meditation is that you learn the
levels and the six powers and the four
states of so there'll be nine levels six
Powers four states of by next you know
notbook so I'll go over it
again you're going to bring your poster
and you going bring a notebook because
everything I'm talking about is on the
poster but sometimes not so
obviously
so there are going to be nine levels of
meditation there going to be six powers
or strength with which you achieve those
levels and then there will be four
states of Mind through which your mind
passes As you move out to the so the
first
level is
achie
so is a Shri in Sanskrit it means
listening uh and uh what it means is
listening to the words of a human
teacher okay so like you can learn
Chinese on you can
buy and have the tap
yell uh but it's so much different than
sitting in the back of a car in Shanghai
and having someone right and having
someone yell at you five times you know
how to say it and correcting you that
the correction part is really important
you say Jim and then they say
she she and you're you know you you have
a human being sitting there and
correcting you you know so
uh means uh listening to the words of a
human being uh directly and you know if
you can't get to
Prescot you don't have chains on your
chat
ler uh you know I'm I'm we're offering
uh this
teachings and we're offering and you can
download but it's not going to be the
same okay human being shy means hearing
at the feet of a human being okay um so
the first level of
meditation uh which is really sort you
could say it's the decision to meditate
right it's the decision to sit down and
and place your mind on the object for
the first time
uh that the is precipitated by U some
teacher who convinces you that this is
going to be useful for you right no
human being will do anything at all
unless they think they'll get something
helpful or beneficial for themselves
this is how we are uh so it's the
teacher's job to inspire you to to think
about what's going to happen to you if
you learn to
meditate and that's turet do so I'm
going to do a little turp do okay
uh there are in Gaya especially in the
monks teachings for the monks CL there
are four traditional forms of sustenance
it's very famous it's called say
[Music]
say uh means literally means food but
here it means sustenance okay she means
for say in Chinese sorry for types
of four types of sustance okay uh the
first one is called say
say you know have you ever
heard anybody know
what area H yeah she said it's an area
there's a there's a province ofc called
K the word means
Province why they would name a province
Province I don't know okay like that's
like me on a state okay but come means a
state but it can also mean
what yeah it can mean your
propensities like your hidden
propensities for your life you know like
some people discover at a certain age
that they were meant to be an upright B
player you see their whole life was
there and then you suddenly you couch
the thing you're like ah like you get
somebody's dads
miraculous instrument you put your hand
on it oh then the come the come you see
your come so come in that sense means a
a little parcel in your heart of of what
you were meant to do what you were meant
to be called it's also called okay
what's another meaning of
do pce a discret piece of
something that's
sorry
yeah for for sorry desire for forance we
live in the desire realm it's all you've
ever
seen uh there are two other Realms that
are happening parallel
universes that are happening parallel to
this world and you can't see them in
meditation that's also called C like an
area of the universe three provinces of
the
universe in as the 18 CS which is
your uh six senses six object senses and
six conscious senses those are also
called the most famous one is
DH which is the object of the
mental and then that became a name of
government
organization so
that's say come in that sense means a
discret bit of something which means
it's defined as something you can bite
off
like a banana is kung because you can
bite off a piece of SW so Kung is the
first kind of
sustenance physical
sust everybody needs it everybody
needs so second kind of
[Music]
say I
just means sorry
next skip that let's do different number
two that's number
three number two is say
say means
sleep probably real sleep or something
okay I need a block of 5 hours and I
can't fun you know I don't know what it
is for you I need seven to eight to be
polite uh and uh that's how you that's
the kind of sustenance everybody needs
sleep most
people most humans need sleep okay and
uh it's a kind of
sustance uh so of course I know that
you're not going to wake up if you wake
up earlier than your roommates you're
going to sit quietly in bed and try not
to what do you call do the Springs too
much or if you have to go PE you're
going to be super quiet
I don't know sit down so they don't hear
any okay
uh that's Nik say people need that Su
they can function okay and so that's the
second kind of
food third one is called you know what
means hope okay hope is the kind of sub
if you have hope for the future if you
have plans for the future if you have a
meaningful project to work on you have a
meaningful
work to do meaningful work to do uh some
kind of hope for the future some kind of
what do they call it
word it's like looking into the looking
forward to something aspiration
aspiration or looking forward to your
life you know like I I want to do this
by next week I you know I'm doing
something important I'm helping caret
Tre you have some kind of U
meaningful future thought
things okay it's called and in the
scriptures they say if there's a horse
which is traveling to the desert by
itself and it starts to die first right
and then suddenly it's going to die in
10 ft so in 10 ft it drops to its knees
and then it's just reached a little
sandon and then it sees a
like 200 yard down the Senter you know
and by All rights it should have died on
the sand it had no more physical
sustenance to to move the legs of the
horse but seeing the water will be no
horse ever died 100 y from water never
no human ever stopped you know like 10
seconds from reaching something makes
hope can sustain you physically to to do
the rest so that's last last
one
[Music]
called
that's uninterrupted concentration okay
is a sustenance for the mind and body
uninterrupted focus on anything is a
necessary sustenance for human beings
okay you cannot live without moments of
uninterrupted Focus you know that's why
I was in a corporate environment for a
long time and and I saw people break
down and M them you know and we work
sometimes you know1 18 hours a day uh
and then uh you would push somebody and
you would give them three more tasks or
they'd be in the middle of the task and
then you'd get a priority you have to
change priorities that's one of the most
destructive things in the corporate
environment you someone's cruising along
on a very difficult job and then you say
wait stop that and do this you know and
then they they handle one Interruption
and they handle two interruptions
interrupt them 10 times in a day
interrupt their focus 10 times a day
change their priority 10 times a day and
you can break anybody okay you can break
any good employee that way you know just
soon as they get focused on one Tas
which is pretty much an impossible Tas
but they're going for it and then you
say stop down and do this you know and
then people break down people just break
so people human
beings uh the mind and the psyche and
the body are sustained by uninterrupted
time to focus that's why uh reading a
book is so enjoyable or making out your
boyfriend or watching a movie or
anything which
is uninterrupted concentration and then
people will get irritable the more you
the more you break your concentration
theying the the middle of something you
know they're really focusing on a movie
or something and then you you say you
know can you wash the
dishes you can break a person like that
right so this Fourth Kind of sustenance
is perhaps the most necessary for
human and that's one of my undoing I'm
doing try I'm trying to sell you on
starting the first level because
somebody has to sell you or you won't do
it there has to be a reason to that I'm
selling you on the first level
you need it to to live you know you
cannot be happy without meditating it's
not going to happen you need times of
uninterrupted focus a human being lives
like that and and if you sub it's like
what do you
call it's like almond milk as opposed to
a Coke in myor with my C you know like I
I might prefer a Coke or a coffee say a
coffee but the almond milk is going to
make me I drink almond milk knowing that
in 2 hours it's going to make me really
smart and focused you know I I control
myself you know I like coffee I I I used
to drink a lot of coffee and then I but
I know that the coffee is not going to
give me what I need and I but I know if
I drink the almond milk which is Less
Pleasant for me at that moment than
coffee I know that in an hour I'm going
to be really you know I my mind is going
to be focused my body is going to be
strong I'm going to feel healthy you
know so meditation is like that
meditation is like the T Zing is say the
decision to partake of thinging is say
is is a really wise one you're busy you
don't have time to meditate you have
other things to do and you you make a
decision and you draw a line and you say
I'm going to meditate it's like drinking
alond milk okay it's like I'd rather do
eal and that's like coffee okay I'd
rather do something that's
add uh cuz that has a sort of shallow
attraction like coffee and but I know if
I take the OM then my mind will be
healthy and strong and and feel
sustained so that's a selling point for
meditation if you
do if you keep your mind on a single
object for 15 minutes in the entire day
it can sustain you in a way that you
cannot
just sitting with your teacher watching
their eyes what does it do for you it
the fact that your mind is not moving to
another object sustains you big time it
sustains your body and your mind and you
become much healthier stronger uh
happier immensely happier and it's weird
somebody say to you just keep your mind
on anything for 15 minutes a day and
you'll be a much happier person it's
because it's sustenance it's a kind of
sust and you can't live without it we've
been living without it and that's why so
many people are
happy it's as if they were woken up
every night every two hours by somebody
and your whole
life the flow of your mind has been
interrupted your whole life by by the
demands of your life and and and what
I'm suggest is check it out do 15
minutes of true sustenance every day and
then you you feel much happier much more
human much more alive you have a real
life okay that's t Okay shy by cha you
gain what bu the sales pitch from your
personal L you get first level that's
what pushes you into first level got it
I want you to learn the levels
why because I want you to be a
teacher because I want you to teach okay
I want you know we went to Asia we we
we've taken about 40 teachers with us
now and the programs are designed that
we have to have 40 teachers we need 300
teachers for the program SE we need 300
teachers uh and you got to learn like
you shouldn't come out in this 10 days
unable to to give somebody what you're
getting right now okay you about nine
levels six Powers four life you must
come out with that okay uh you must
learn to teach it
okay we'll do one more brief now we'll
stop how many minutes have we
take it's all right it's not
quity it's not the quity with meditation
it's not quality it's just
quality 15 minutes of quality meditation
was all right so remember the first
session we did did five minutes